Guide to the New-York Historical Society Ephemera Record Group 1839-2019 NYHS-RG 14
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society ephemera
1839-2019
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 14
15.6 Linear feet in 26 document boxes, five card boxes, and three oversize folders.
The New-York Historical Society ephemera record group is comprised of print materials generated for distribution by the institution between 1839 and 2019 and documents N-YHS communication, programming, outreach, and promotion throughout its years of operation. Ephemera includes admission tickets; invitations; informational brochures; souvenir exhibition programs and checklists; event programs, handouts, calendars and schedules; library, museum, and membership announcements; bookplates and stationery; posters, postcards, flyers, and other promotional items.
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society ephemera record group is comprised of print materials generated for public distribution by the institution between 1839 and 2019, and documents N-YHS communication, programming, outreach, and promotion over its years of operation.
Materials include (in order of prominence) admission tickets; invitations; souvenir exhibition programs, checklists and small pamphlet-style catalogues; event programs, handouts, calendars and schedules; meeting and election notices; library, museum, and membership announcements; publication and other informational brochures; blank ballots, order forms, membership applications, and stationery; bookplates; form letters; posters, postcards, flyers, and other promotional items; and circulars for subscriptions to building initiatives, the Publication Fund, or other endeavors.
Within the context of this record group, ephemera does not include newsletters or other periodically published bulletins, substantially sized and/or bound volumes, three-dimensional artifacts, items intended for sale, or paper materials not produced in bulk printings. Other items commonly relocated by the archivist to other record groups during processing include: press releases, press kits, clippings and other publicity materials; gift shop catalogs and products; and staff notices, memos, and other items circulated exclusively within the institution. Most notated or otherwise personalized materials have been relocated to other record groups, though a few such documents remain with the ephemera.
Series I. Ephemera Files contains chronological files of N-YHS print material created and distributed between 1839 and 2019.
Series II. Ephemera Scrapbooks contains materials compiled into scrapbooks over time by N-YHS staff between 1843 and 1985; the content largely overlaps with Series I.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Ephemera can be found in several of the other record groups that are processed and available to researchers, though usually with contextual information. Examples of record groups that have material especially related to the New-York Historical Society ephemera record group (NYHS-RG 14) are as follows:
The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2) includes various N-YHS distribution materials created between 1804 and 1979.
The New-York Historical Society celebratory and memorial event record group (NYHS-RG 15) includes invitations, event programs, tickets, and other material associated with select special events hosted by N-YHS between 1854 and 1954.
The New-York Historical Society press clippings (NYHS-RG 7) includes scrapbooks, some of which hold ephemera.
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society ephemera (NYHS-RG 14) record group is organized in two series:
Series I. Ephemera Files (1839-2019)
Series II. Ephemera Scrapbooks (1843-1985)
Access Restrictions
The record group is open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact [reference email address] prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Accruals Note
The record group will continue to receive ongoing accruals of ephemera as it is collected, though these items will not necessarily be compiled in any systematic manner.
Brochures.; Calendars.; Ephemera.; Exhibition catalogs; Invitations.; Programs (documents).; Promotional materials.; Scrapbooks.; Tickets.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Libraries -- New York (State) -- New York -- Public relations.; Museums -- New York (State) -- New York -- Public relations.; Printed ephemera -- New York (State) -- New York.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives; New-York Historical Society -- Public relations
- Series I. Ephemera Files, 1839-2019; 13.1 Linear feet in 20 document boxes, five card boxes, and one oversize folder.
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series contains chronological files of N-YHS print material created and distributed between 1839 and 2012.
  Multiple copies of small-format event announcements and tickets, dating between 1871 and 1982, are stored separately in card boxes. These contain 19th- to early 20th-century monthly and annual meeting notices sent to members, often highlighting a special guest lecturer and presentation topic. Circa the 1920s, announcements and invitations for exhibition previews and concerts also start to appear. Around the mid-1940s, N-YHS incorporated film screenings into its event programming (often projecting titles from its own collection), and began hosting an increasing number of exhibition previews, private receptions, and board of trustees events. Two annual events represented throughout the files from this period forward are the Strawberry Festival, held in late spring, and St. Nicholas Day Festival, a 19th-century tradition revived in 1939 as a holiday season celebration.
  Researchers interested in specific periods should also consult the folder files, where further invitations and tickets may appear, in addition to calendars, gallery floor plans, exhibition programs and checklists, and other informational, educational, and promotional items for N-YHS special events, exhibitions, public programming, development, membership, publications, and library/museum collections and services. Calendars and handouts for conferences and symposia hosted by and at N-YHS are also present. Ephemera produced for fundraising and donor events proliferates from the 1990s onward, including materials for the History Makers Gala (annual benefit held since the mid-1980s), movie premieres (The Age of Innocence, The Wings of the Dove), and other society events held onsite (e.g., fashion show by the design house Halston). A small amount of 19th and early 20th century fundraising/subscription circulars and other documents for building construction, general support, Publication Fund, and acquisition of artworks is also in the series.
  A diverse group of outside organizations are represented in the series, many of which held meetings and other events onsite at N-YHS, or collaborated on exhibitions or other programming. These include the Daughters of the Revolution, Columbia University, Allied Artists of America, Holland Society, Maiden Lane Historical Society, School Art League Steamship Historical Society of America, and the Long Island Preservation of Antiquities.
  The end of the series features general information brochures and/or undated materials for the institution, its library and museum, and the fundraising and membership departments. Other files contain blank postcards, stationery, and bookplates.
  Arrangement Note
  The bulk of the Series I files are arranged chronologically.
  Commencing with the 1990 files, a prior staff member maintained chronological order, but individually foldered all materials by event or exhibition. Folders containing general, miscellaneous, and year-spanning materials introduce each year's run.
  General information and undated materials for specific N-YHS departments, and discrete groups of single format materials, are listed at the end of the series container list.
  - Ephemera. 1839-1859, 1839-1859, Undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes dinner ticket for N-YHS 40th Anniversary dinner on November 20, 1844 signed on back by Egbert Benson; unsigned tickets of introduction "To Be Delivered at the Door;" one "New-York Gallery ticket; and transferable Member's Tickets. (Undated materials estimated to be from mid 19th century).
  - Ephemera. 1860-1869 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes annual report of the Committee on Fine Arts (1861-1862); circular for the John Jay Audubon subscription fund (April 1863); circular for the Bryan and Jarves pictures (March 1964); the Rules of the Executive Committee (1864); select tickets have names written on them, others have acquisition notes on back.
    Ticket for Strawberry Festival (June 7, 1864) accompanied by 1976 letter from donor Edward Naumburg indicating this is the first recorded evidence of the N-YHS event, despite beliefs it began as early as 1855.
  - Ephemera. 1870-1879 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera. 1871-1935. Announcements and Tickets (Offsite-box 16, Cards -)
  - Ephemera. 1880-1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera. 1884-1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ephemera. 1888-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ephemera. 1900-1904 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes letterpress printing of J.L. Beekman poem "A Goddess Distressed," dated December 13 & 14, 1901, relating to the need for building funds.
  - Ephemera. 1904. N-YHS Centennial (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes program featuring menu, reprinting of original meeting minutes, and illustrations of former N-YHS locations; seating plan for the banquet held at Delmonico's restaurant.
  - Ephemera. 1905-1910 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes first circular announcing and recruiting donors to the Founders Fund; September 1, 1908 notice of relocation of collections to new location on Central Park West and closure of both buildings until further notice; August 23, 1909 announcement and description of stand for members and their families to view the parades of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Ephemera. 1911-1919 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes December 5. 1919 circular issued by Executive Committee combatting recent accusations of neglect made against N-YHS management.
  - Ephemera. 1920-1922 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ephemera. 1923-1924 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ephemera. 1925-1929 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ephemera. 1930-1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ephemera. 1933-1935 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes tickets for January 2, 1934 address by Bella C. Landauer, "An Informal Talk on My Collection of Lottery Items, Trade Cards, Transportation Literature, etc."
  - Ephemera. 1936-1938 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes images of new wing construction; May 5, 1936 program for Jenny Lind songs performed by soprano Crystal Waters (autographed by Waters).
  - Ephemera. 1939-1945. Announcements and Tickets (Offsite-box 17, Cards -)
    Includes ephemera indicating an N-YHS graphic design shift from traditional serif and blackletter-style to the sans serif Futura typeface in 1939.
  - Ephemera. 1939 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes tickets (one for Miss S.H. Haveland) and guidelines for historical cruise aboard the Steamer Chauncey M. Depew on September 14, 1939; pamphlet on "The Story of the New-York Historical Society," which includes descriptions of the new museum galleries.
  - Ephemera. 1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera. 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ephemera. 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes a pamphlet describing the Thompson Homestead Memorial, a museum at East Hampton, Long Island, owned and operated by N-YHS in the 1940s.
  - Ephemera. 1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes handout on procedure for staff and visitors during an air raid, dated January 13, 1943.
  - Ephemera. 1944 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera. 1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ephemera. 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes type-written supplement to 1946 Strawberry Festival invitations: "In co-operation with Mr. Hoover's emergency food conservation program, each person will be limited to one portion."
  - Ephemera. 1946-1954. Announcements and Tickets, 1946-1955 (Offsite-box 18, Cards -)
  - Ephemera. 1950-1959 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-2)
    Includes postcards from the "New York Fashion in 1869" exhibition; pamphlets on the Carriage Collection and "Collection of Steamboat Pictures that the New-York Historical Society should possess..." and catalog for the DeWitt McClellan Lockman memorial exhibition.
  - Ephemera. 1952-1959. Event Calendars (2 folders), 1952-1959; 1969-1970 (Box OS-1, Folder 3-4)
    Includes large seasonal calendars of events, listing special exhibitions, motion picture and music series, education events, lectures and gallery talks, and basic visitor information.
  - Ephemera. 1955-1982. Announcements and Tickets, 1956-1982 (Offsite-box 19, Cards -)
  - Ephemera. 1960-1969 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3-4)
    Includes letterpress printing of short-title list of rare books, broadsides, maps, and manuscripts on display in the 1969 exhibition "Treasures of Americana from the Library of the New-York Historical Society."
  - Ephemera. 1970-1972 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5-6)
    Includes circulars on Bicentennial Planning Commission and "Audubon and His World" exhibition of original Birds of America watercolors; handout for the 1971 inaugural exhibition of the N-YHS Library Gallery, "Classics of Seventeenth-Century Americana."
  - Ephemera. 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ephemera. 1975 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera. 1976 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera. 1977 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2-3)
    Includes revised 1977 edition of pamphlet "The Story of the New-York Historical Society."
  - Ephemera. 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera. 1980 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera. 1981 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera. 1982 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Ephemera. 1983 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5-7)
  - Ephemera. 1984 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8-9)
    Includes pamphlet for N-YHS lixury cruise along the coast of Canada and southern Alaska on the Royal Viking Star.
  - Ephemera. 1985 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
    Includes three copies of the John J. Audubon first day of issue stamp in related cover.
  - Ephemera. 1986 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Ephemera. 1987 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5-7)
    Includes brochures for the debut season of six N-YHS walking tours, "New-York Walks."
  - Ephemera. 1988 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Ephemera. 1989 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4-6)
    Includes invitation to opening, and advertisement for woodblock printed in commemoration, of the Paper and Book Conservation Laboratory.
  - Ephemera. 1990 (14 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-14)
    Includes Christmas card hand-illustrated by Laird Ogden depicting and autographed by staff of the Print, Photographs, and Architectural Collections department (see also: 1991 General folder).
  - Ephemera. 1991 (20 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15-34)
    Includes promotional postcards for new hours of operation featuring Irving Browning photographs accompanied by note: "Tom [Dunning] - This is all contraband -- all copies supposedly destroyed - but it was given out at Paine Webber opening!! Note caption on reverse and what you can read on front side. Wendy 9/24." Includes materials for The Jewish Museum during its time housed at N-YHS while its building was renovated.
  - Ephemera. 1992 (16 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-16)
    Includes extensive selection of brochures printed for "Markers of Change: Documents of American History" exhibition, on topics ranging from John Winthrop's 17th-century sermon "A Modell of Christian Charity," to Ulysses S. Grant's terms of surrender at Appomattox.
  - Ephemera. 1993 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 17-19)
  - Ephemera. 1994 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 20-22)
  - Ephemera. 1995 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 23-27)
  - Ephemera. 1995 May-December (5 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-5)
  - Ephemera. Undated, [1995-2004] (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
    Includes walking tour maps and handout from Halston fashion show hosted at N-YHS.
  - Ephemera. 1996 (9 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7-15)
  - Ephemera. 1997 (11 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 16-26)
  - Ephemera. 1998 (19 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-19)
  - Ephemera. 1999 (11 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 20-30)
    Includes promotional postcards for the new N-YHS website at www.nyhistory.org.
  - Ephemera. 1999 May-December (13 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1-13)
    Includes invitation to August 5 memorial celebration for John F. Kennedy, Jr. hosted at N-YHS by George Magazine and Hachette Filipacchi Magazines.
  - Ephemera. 2000 (10 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 14-23)
  - Ephemera. 2001 (4 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 24-27)
    Includes letter from Mayor Rudolph Guiliani addressed to all attendees of the opening of the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture.
  - Ephemera. 2002 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 28-32)
  - Ephemera. 2003 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 33-34)
  - Ephemera. 2004 (7 folders) (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-7)
  - Ephemera. 2005 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8)
    Includes issue of the "New York Amsterdam News" written and distributed in conjunction with the 2005-2006 "Slavery in New York" exhibition.
  - Ephemera. 2006 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 9)
  - Ephemera. 2007 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 10)
  - Ephemera. 2008 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
  - Ephemera. 2009 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 12)
  - Ephemera. 2010 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 13)
  - Ephemera. 2011 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 13, Folder 14-15)
  - Ephemera. 2012 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera. 2013 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera. 2014 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera. 2015 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera. 2016 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5)
  - Ephemera. 2017-2019 (Offsite-box 31)
  - Ephemera. Undated, [1990-2012] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6)
    Includes Festival of St. Nicholas handouts: notes written by Carol Zicklin (adapted from the Papers of John Pintard) and reprintings of Clement Clarke Moore's "T'was the Night Before Christmas" manuscript and the published 1848 edition.
  - Ephemera. Library, [1890-1990] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 7)
    Includes admittance cards for affiliated members of the industrial arts field and various form letters sent in response to research inquiries.
  - Ephemera. Museum, [1880-1950] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 8)
    Includes notice to members encouraging them to introduce visitors of the city to the exhibition galleries (late 19th-century); blank invitations to become N-YHS member; floor plan guides for museum visitors (ca. 1930-1945).
  - Ephemera. General Information (1 of 3), [1850-1940] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 9)
    Includes pamphlet on N-YHS publications through 1924 and early 20th-century membership handout.
  - Ephemera. General Information (2 of 3), [1960-1995] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 10)
    Includes general information brochures for the museum, library, school programs, and Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections; several versions of promotional brochure titled "The Importance of Being Hyphenated."
  - Ephemera. General Information (3 of 3), [1996-2010] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 11)
  - Ephemera, Miscellaneous, 1950s-2011 (Offsite-box 20)
  - Ephemera. Fundraising and Development, [1965-1995] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 12)
    Includes brochures on planned giving and coroporate sponsorships; blank acknowledgement for gifts; blank donation form listing amount of gift, format of acknowledgment, and installment schedule; "With the Compliments of the New-York Historical Society" gift cards (all undated).
  - Ephemera. Membership, [1980-circa 2004] (Offsite-box 14, Folder 13)
    Includes general information brochures about N-YHS membership.
  - Ephemera. Postcards, ca. 1920 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 14)
    Includes multiple images of 170 Central Park West building, reading room, and Henry Dexter Hall as well as highlights from collection such as the Beekman Family Coach.
  - Ephemera. Bookplates, ca. 1940-1960 (Offsite-box 21, Cards -)
    Includes bookplates for volumes purchased using the Trust Fund of Lathrop Colgate Harper, Mrs. Lathrop Colgate Harper Fund in Memory of Francis P. Harper, and the James B. Wilbur fund; bookplates featuring blank space for entering purchaser name; and copperplate illustrated with N-YHS logo and address.
  - Ephemera. Bookplate Sheets (2 folders), ca. 1900-1950 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 15-16)
    Includes sheets of labels for library volumes purchased using the Demilt Fund, Grosvenor Fund, Thomas Fund, Ewer Legacy, and Griswold Legacy. In poor condition.
  - Ephemera. Folders, ca. 1985-1995 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 17)
    Includes folders used for press kits and other sets of distribution materials.
  - Ephemera. Stationery, [1950-2005] (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1-4)
    Includes blank memorandum forms, gift acknowledgments, package labels, envelopes, and other stationery featuring N-HYS letterhead. The bulk features red letterpress printing, with some letterheads personalized for James B. Bell (Director) and Larry E. Sullivan (Librarian), Norman Pearlstein (Chairman), Betsy Gotbaum (President), or Wilbur L. Ross, Jr. and Herbert S. Winokur, Jr. (Co-Chairmen).
  - Ephemera. Staff Telephone Directories, 1982-2009 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5)
    Directories includes staff person's name and department (earlier directories) or title (later directories), or sometimes both, thereby providing an overview of staffing.
  - Ephemera. Program & Exhibition Listings, 2005-2019 (Offsite-box 31)
    Scope and Contents
    Semi-annual booklets distributed to the public listing upcoming programs, speakers, exhibitions, etc.
  - Excess Ephemera. 1930-1955 [Restricted] (Offsite-box 22)
    This box includes only excess copies of tickets and other ephemera culled from the folders in the record group. Because the material is redundant it is available for internal use only.
  - Excess Ephemera. 1965-2012 [Restricted] (Offsite-box 23)
  - Excess Ephemera. 1985-2000 [Restricted] (Offsite-box 24)
- Series II. Ephemera Scrapbooks, 1849-1985; 2.5 Linear feet in 6 document boxes and one oversize folder.
  This series contains chronologically assembled scrapbook pages of N-YHS print material created and distributed between 1843 and 1985. A majority of the materials -- which were alternately glued, stapled, or slid into plastic sleeves -- overlap with content found in Series I, though with some variation. Due to varying degrees of paper brittleness and adhesive deterioration in many of the files, researchers are advised to consult Series I first.
  Early scrapbooks are captioned by prior staff, whom also prepared indexes based on lecturer name, and inputted description of events for which they did not maintain associated ephemera. Further details and specific highlights of individual scrapbooks may be found in the container list.